| T. V. Raman |
|---------------------------------|
| Google Research |
| Phone: (650) 799-5724 |
| E-mail: (tv.raman.tv@gmail.com) |
| http://emacspeak.sf.net/raman |

Summary

I am an accomplished Computer Scientist with over 17 years of leadership experience in advanced technology development. During this time, I have authored 3 books and filed over 50 patents; my work on auditory interfaces has been profiled in mainstream publications including the New York Times and Scientific American. I presently lead accessibility for Google Android and Google Chrome; I have leading edge expertise in developing auditory interfaces for mobile devices and Web applications. Earlier, I led the definition of numerous W3C standards including XForms and Aural CSS.

Objective

Deliver technologies that enable ubiquitous, eyes-free access to the emerging Web platform from a wide variety of devices ranging from smart phones and tablets to network-based computers. Speech is the next dimension in user interfaces, and I am developing application frameworks that combine speech technologies with the power of the Web Cloud to deliver innovative solutions that enable anytime, anywhere access.

Work experience

• Google, Google Research, Mountain View, CA

Research Scientist.

Aug 2005-Present.

Android Access Led Accessibility from its inception to deliver many innovative end-user solutions. ChromeVox Led the design of a complete accessibility solution that is built entirely of Web technologies. Accessible Search Built an innovative classifier for measuring Accessibility that is integrated into Google.

• IBM Research, Almaden Research Center, San Jose, CA

Research Staff Member: Architect, Conversational Multimodal WWW.

Aug 1999-Aug 2005.

XForms Authoring applications for the next generation WWW.

RDC Reusable Dialog Components to speech-enable the Web.

X+V Speech-enabling XHTML to create a multimodal Web.

• Adobe Systems, Advanced Technology Group, San Jose, CA

Oct 1995-Aug 1999.

Senior Computer Scientist: Dynamic publishing on the Internet. PDF2HTML Developed the PDF to HTML translator bundled with major Web search engines —access.adobe.com. XML Metadata Developed an XML-based virtual document architecture to enable content reuse.

• Digital Equipment Corporation, Cambridge Research Lab, Cambridge, MA

Research Staff: Retriever –A Multimodal Web Interface.

Feb 1994-Oct 1995.

• Intel Corporation, Intel Architecture Labs, Hillsboro, OR

Summer Associate: Prototyped an email telephony interface.

Jun-Aug 1993.

• Xerox Palo Alto Research Center, Palo Alto, CA

Summer Associate: Prototyped a new reading machine architecture.

May-Aug 1991.

Education

- Cornell University, Ithaca, NY
 - PhD. Applied Mathematics:

Aug 1989–Jan 1994.

Awarded the ACM Doctoral Dissertation Award, 1994.

Thesis: Audio System For Technical Readings. Adviser: Prof. David Gries, Computer Science.

– MS Computer Science:

- Indian Institute of Technology, Bombay, India: MSc Computer Science: GPA: 9.78/10.00 July 1989.
- University of Pune, Pune, India: BA Mathematics:

May 1987.

Selected Awards and Honors

| • Computerworld Award Smithsonian Institution Emacspeak: Complete Audio Desktop. | April 1999. |
|--|-------------|
| • Association of Computing Machinery (ACM) Doctoral Dissertation Award | 1994. |
| • Intel Graduate Fellowship Intel Corporation, CA | 1992. |
| • Graduate Fellowship Cornell University. | 1989. |
| • President's Silver Medal Indian Institute of Technology, Bombay. | 1989. |
| • Sir Cusrow Wadia Gold Medal University of Pune. | 1987. |
| • Sir Ness Wadia Gold Medal Wadia College, Pune. | 1984. |

Selected Books and Patents

| Locating My Publications | | | | |
|--------------------------|-----|-----|------|--|
| Google Scholar | ACM | CSB | DBLP | |

- 1 T. V. Raman. XForms XML Powered Web Forms. Addison Wesley, 2003.
- 2 T. V. Raman. Audio System For Technical Readings. LNCS 1410, Springer Verlag, 1998.
- 3 T. V. Raman. Auditory User Interfaces. Kluwer Academic Publishers, 1997.
- 4 T. V. Raman. Generating audio renderings of digitized works. Cornell. U.S. Patent 5,572,625, 1996.
- 5 T. V. Raman and Jim Larson. Telephone access system. Intel Corporation. U.S. Patent 5,825,854, 1998.
- 6 T. V. Raman. Multimodal information presentation system. DEC. U.S. Patent 5,748,186, 1998.
- 7 T. V. Raman. Data stream processing on networks. Adobe Systems. U.S. Patent 6,134,598, 2000.
- 8 T. V. Raman and John Warnock. Digitized speech and text. Adobe Systems. U.S. Patent 6,151,576, 2000.
- 9 T. V. Raman. Document description format. Adobe Systems. U.S. Patent 6,249,794, , 2001.
- 10 T. V. Raman. Speech interface for computer application programs DEC. U.S. Patent 6,289,312, 2001.
- 11 T. V. Raman. et al Dialog management in a multimodal environment IBM. U.S. Patent 6,839,896, 2005.

Selected Publications And Articles

- 1 TV Raman. Toward 2 w, beyond web 2.0. Communications of the ACM, 52(2):52-59, 2009.
- 2 T. V. Raman. Netsurfing without a monitor. Scientific American, March 1997. Special Internet Edition.
- 3 T. V. Raman. User interface —a means to an end. Dr. Dobb's Journal, August 1997.
- 4 Wayt Gibbs. Profile: T. V. raman: Envisioning speech. Scientific American, September 1996.
- 5 Brian Hayes. Speaking of mathematics. American Scientist, 84(2), March-April 1996.
- 6 T. V. Raman. Cascaded speech style sheets. WWW6 Conference, CA., April 1997.
- 7 T. V. Raman. Audio System for Technical Readings. PhD thesis, Cornell University, May 1994.
- 8 T. V. Raman. Emacspeak –a speech interface. CHI96, April 1996.
- 9 T. V. Raman et al. XForms 1.0 W3c, October, 2003. http://www.w3.org/tr/xforms
- 10 T. V. Raman et al. Adding Spoken Interaction To XHTML W3c, December, 2001.
- 11 T. V. Raman Collecting Business Critical Information Using XForms XML Journal, April, 2003.

Other Interests

My favorite hobby is recreational mathematics. I enjoy working on puzzles, especially those that involve an intuitive feel for mathematics. One of the things I enjoyed doing the most in the early eighties was to solve the Rubik's cube faster than anyone else around me, on an average of about thirty seconds! During the last few years, discovering Zome Systems for building complex polyhedra has helped rekindle my interest in polyhedral geometry. I am also interested in linguistics and can speak about eight languages, including French, German and several Indian languages.